"What Is Taurine in Energy Drinks and
Does It Enhance Cognitive or Athletic Performance?"
Energy drinks
are widely consumed
in the United States,
with sales exceeding
350 million gallons
(1.324 billion liters).
But there's only like
335 million people in the US,
so, we each average more
than a gallon (3.8 L) a year?
Is it just the caffeine
that people are after?
A major ingredient
in popular energy drinks
is taurine.
What is that?
Taurine is one
of the most abundant
free amino acids in our body,
free as in
not incorporated into proteins.
We make it in our own bodies,
that's why it's
considered non-essential,
as in we don't have
to get any in our diet.
However, premature infants
are vulnerable
to taurine deficiency
because they initially lack
some of the enzymes needed
to synthesize taurine,
but breast milk provides
all the taurine they need,
and it's often added
to infant formula as well.
We aren't the only
animals who make it.
The name taurine derives
from the Latin taurus,
meaning bull or ox,
because taurine
was first isolated
from the bile of an ox in 1827,
decades before
it was discovered in people.
It's funny, in my search
of the medical literature,
I kept coming across
articles on taurine surgery.
What does that mean?
That's what they call surgery
for bullfighting injuries.
Anyway, taurine was
first isolated in the 1800s,
but not much was known
about this molecule
until the 1990s,
after we found low levels
in preterm formula-fed infants.
Even through taurine
isn't incorporated
into proteins,
it plays important roles
throughout our body.
Clues to its importance
include the fact
that our body has not one,
not two, but at least five
pathways to make it.
And we make a lot of it.
If you look down
at the bathroom scale
and it says 200 pounds (90 kg),
about one-fifth
of a pound (90g)
of that is straight taurine.
Other clues can be found
in where it's made.
The main pathway enzyme
is found not only in our liver
but in sensitive tissues
like the eye, brain, kidney,
breast milk-producing glands,
and our reproductive organs.
The levels in sperm
suggest a protective effect.
Taurine is described
as a major antioxidant,
but it's really
only good at squelching
one type of free radical,
but that free radical
produces pro-aging toxins,
like advanced glycation
end products,
so, that squelching activity
is an important function.
In addition to our brain,
taurine is also found
concentrated in our muscles,
where it's involved
in energy production.
Presumably, that's why
it's put into energy drinks.
Does taurine help
with cognitive
or physical performance?
Probably neither,
like in this study,
no benefit for either
physical or cognitive ability,
with some studies suggesting
taurine actually undercuts
some of caffeine's
beneficial effects
on cognition or vigor.
Or that it helps with
one kind of cognitive task
but hurts
performance of another.
Taurine may be more
red herring than Red Bull,
as the human studies
often cited to support it
have been improperly designed
and lack
the appropriate controls.
Put all the studies together,
and there is little evidence
of taurine increasing
endurance exercise,
and it's unclear whether
there are any sports benefits
like reducing muscle soreness
or speeding recovery.
Taurine ingestion
might even be detrimental
to maximal muscle power
in noncaffeine consumers.
The picture
is just really unclear,
which is why I never
paid much attention to it
until, boom,
this study came out,
suggesting taurine deficiency
was a driver of aging.
It was published after
I had already submitted
the manuscript
for my longevity book,
How Not to Age;
so, I've been eager
to dive into the topic
to see if there was anything
there.
As we age,
the taurine levels
in our body fall
by as much as 80 percent.
This may be due
to the depletion
of the taurine-synthesizing
enzyme in our liver,
suggesting we may need to start
getting more taurine
in our diet as we age.
The reason it was concluded
that taurine
was a driver of aging
is because,
when attempts were made
to restore youthful levels
in animals
through taurine supplementation,
this reversal
of taurine deficiency
increased the health
of worms, rodents, and primates,
and increased the lifespan
of worms and rodents.
We'll dig into
this important study, next.